We will now begin the first-class mage exam.
现在开始一级魔法使选拔测验
You will battle in parties. All 57 participants
全体57名考生 将以小队为单位进行战斗
will be put in parties of three to take this exam.
每队共三名考生来参加考试
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
See, you can do it if you put your mind to it…
你看吧 只要下定决心 你就能做到…
You think so?
是这样吗？
Lawine is rough,
拉比涅虽然粗暴
but she's a good leader to me.
但她总是好好引领着我向前走
Tomorrow will be our first time fighting a dragon.
明天终于要首次跟龙对战了
Are you scared, Eisen? You're trembling.
你怕了吗 艾泽？你在发抖
-Yeah. -I see. Well then…
-是啊 -这样啊 那么…
-You're really scared? -Yeah.
-你真的很怕啊？ -对
I see…
是吗…
I'm scared too.
我也害怕
Where is this conversation going?
这什么对话啊？
I was trying to raise everyone's morale like other adventurers do.
我本想和其他冒险者那样 鼓舞大家的士气
But sorry…
抱歉啊
I guess it didn't work.
看来这样做没有用呢
No, thanks to you I'm less nervous now.
不会 多亏有你 我比较不紧张了
Himmel, just be yourself.
辛美尔 你就做你自己就好了
I'm sure each party of adventurers handles things differently.
我相信每支冒险队伍 处理这种情况的方式都不同
I guess so.
说得也是
I see. I guess each party really does handle things differently.
原来如此 每个小队的处理方式确实都不同
We finally caught a Stille.
终于抓到陨铁鸟了
Now we can relax for the time being.
这下总算能安心了
How optimistic of you.
说得还真是悠哉
This is where the really hard part begins.
接下来才是最难熬的部分
We must protect the Stille
我们必须守住陨铁鸟
from other parties who will try to steal it from us.
不让其他小队的人偷走才行
Now it's time to fight each other.
再来就是对战的时间了
All right, let's summarize our observations of the Stille.
好 那么我们总结一下 对陨铁鸟的观察结果
First of all, just like Frieren said,
首先 正如芙莉莲所说
that bird flies at supersonic speed.
它们的飞行速度堪比音速
It's impossible to match that speed.
那种速度根本不可能追得上
Plus, it's as tough as a dragon
此外 它们的身体跟龙一样强壮
so it won't budge with ordinary offensive magic.
一般攻击魔法根本起不了作用
Restraints don't work either.
也无法束缚它
On top of that, it's hypersensitive to mana.
除此之外 它们对魔力有很敏锐的感知力
It flies away even when you approach it while suppressing your mana.
就算在抑制魔力的情况下靠近它 还是会被它发现然后逃走
But the biggest problem is that
但最大的问题在于
because Stilles barely have any mana,
因为陨铁鸟本身几乎没有魔力可言
we can't use mana detection.
也无法用魔力感知侦测它
Thanks to that, we have no clue where they are
拜此所赐 我们无从得知它们的位置
or how many there are.
也不知道它们的总数
In the end, we were only able to
结果我们昨天早上
spot them three times yesterday morning.
总共也才看到它们三次而已
I think they're being cautious because the candidates are searching for them.
因为考生正在到处找它们的踪迹 已经让它们升起警戒心了
Worst-case scenario, they may never appear again.
最糟的情况 就是它们可能再也不会现身
But even if we do find one,
即便能找到一只
we have no idea how to catch it.
也不知道要如何捕捉它
Don't worry about that part.
这点就不用担心了
Actually, last night,
其实昨天晚上
I was testing out a spell that might help in catching a Stille.
我在试验一种魔法 对于捕捉陨铁鸟应该能帮上忙
Oh yeah, you were doing something.
对耶 你昨晚确实在做些什么
-What kind of spell is it? -I already showed you, Kanne.
-那是什么魔法？ -我让你看过了喔 康涅
A spell that captures a bird.
是捕鸟魔法
Back when there were a lot more mages
在那个魔法使人数众多
and magic was more common than now,
魔法比现在要来得普遍的年代
a clan that lived off of hunting developed this folk magic.
有个以捕鸟维生的民族 开发出这个民间魔法
Now that I think about it, you stopped it using magic.
说起来 你确实是用魔法束缚住它了
But wasn't that a monster and not a bird?
可是那是魔物 不是鸟啊？
Well, it's folk magic.
这个毕竟是民间魔法
It seems to capture anything that looks like a bird.
只要看起来像鸟的都能抓的住
It's a strong restraining spell, so I think it'll work on a Stille too.
这种束缚魔法威力强大 应该连陨铁鸟都能抓住
Why were you keeping that a secret?
那你为什么现在才说出来？
If we had used that, we could've caught one yesterday.
昨天就用上的话 那早就抓到鸟了
It's not that simple.
事情没那么简单
This spell's range is 50 centimeters.
这种魔法的作用范围是50公分
You have to get that close for it to work.
距离要够近才能起作用
Fifty centimeters?
50公分？
How close have we gotten to it?
至今为止 我们最接近它的距离是多少？
The closest was three meters.
最近的那次是3米
But it seemed like it already sensed us
但是距离20米的时候
when we were 20 meters away.
它就已经发现我们了
We're just one step away, I guess.
就只差一步了呢
That's a very big step.
还真是好大一步
Let me ask, just in case.
保险起见 我先问一下
The two of you can't stall the Stille with your magic, right?
你们无法用你们的魔法 抓住陨铁鸟吧？
If I can freeze it, it may be possible.
如果能冻住它 也许办得到
But since it's sensitive to mana and so tough, it's hard to freeze.
但它的魔力感知很敏锐 身体又很强硬 很难冻住它
It'll probably get away before I can stop it.
大概在封住它的行动前 就会被它逃掉了
With my magic, I can easily stall it as long as
如果是我的魔法 只要在有大量水源的地方
there's a large amount of water.
我就能轻易封住它的行动
But the magic I use only manipulates water,
但是我用的魔法只能操纵水
so I can't generate water itself.
本身并无法产生水源
That means I can't use it unless there is water around.
也就是说 附近没水就无法用了
Mana doesn't transfer well through bodies of water
如果是大量水体 没有事先
so it'll be difficult unless I infuse the water with mana beforehand.
在水里注入魔力的话 就会很难控制
Only if it's dispersed like rain,
除非是像雨水这样四散的水体
can I manipulate large quantities of water instantly.
我就能即刻进行大量操控
But if I infuse the water with mana,
但要是在水里注入魔力的话
Stilles, who are sensitive to mana, would never approach.
对魔力那么敏感的陨铁鸟 就绝对不会靠近了
Never approach?
不会靠近？
I see, they won't approach, huh?
这样啊 不会靠近吗？
This plan may work.
这个作战计划或许可行
I agree that it's not a bad idea, but it's risky.
确实是个不错的点子 但风险很高
It'll turn all other parties against us.
这样一来就要与所有小队为敌了
But we probably won't be able to catch one otherwise.
但不这么做的话 大概也抓不到陨铁鸟
Are you scared, Lawine?
你怕了吗 拉比涅？
Ouch! They'll rip out!
好痛啊…要被扯掉啦！
Fine! Let's do it!
我知道了 就这么做吧！
4TH PARTY LAND, SECOND-CLASS MAGE
（第四小队 二级魔法使 兰托）
For now, let's hide here and make it through the end of the exam.
总之 就先躲在这里 努力撑到考试结束吧
What? How boring.
什么？好无聊啊
If you're a mage, you should fight with confidence.
是魔法使的话 就应该拿出自信对战啊
If you're a mage, you should also avoid unnecessary conflicts.
也应该避免无谓的战斗
First, we'll have to fill up on water.
躲起来之前先去补充水分吧
I believe there was a lake at the center.
我记得试场中央有一座湖
I'm glad we were able to catch a Stille early on.
话说回来 这么早就能抓住陨铁鸟真是太好了
As long as we hide until sundown,
再来只要躲到日落
we can pass the first stage of the exam.
就能通过第一阶段的考试了
-What's wrong? -Apparently, things won't be that easy.
-怎么了？ -看来事情不会那么容易呢
I thought this was a road,
这里看起来像是道路
but it's a dried up riverbed.
但其实是干涸的河床
And I saw a few others that looked like this.
这样的地方还不只一两个
If I remember correctly, they've put up a barrier around the exam location.
我没记错的话 试场周遭已经设下了结界
Yeah, that's common for these exams.
没错 在这类考试中这很常见
It's a powerful antimatter barrier that won't let a speck of dust through.
连一丝灰尘都飘不出去的强力结界
Does it also not let water through?
难道连水都过不去吗？
Looking at how dry it is,
就河床干涸的程度来看
the barrier must've been put up more than a week ago.
他们应该是在一周以前就设下了结界
Then most of the water
那么大部分的水
must have flowed into the lake at the center of the basin.
应该都已经流往中央的大湖了
We candidates, are living beings,
我们考生也是生物
so we need water to function.
必须要有水源才能活动
But that doesn't mean
但那不表示
the candidates are all gathered around the lake.
所有考生都会聚集在湖周围吧
True,
没错
we are able to carry our own water.
我们可以自己带水
But the same doesn't apply to Stilles who are also living beings.
但同样作为生物的陨铁鸟就不行了
I see.
原来如此
So the people who realized this
所以明白这一点的人
are lying in wait by the biggest source of water, the lake.
就会在最大的水源 也就是在湖畔守株待兔吧
All right, give up on getting water.
好吧 那就决定了 不补充水分了
That's going a little too far.
那也做得太过头了吧
I'm already parched.
我已经渴到不行了
I'm sure we can find a little pond.
应该还是能找到小一点的池子吧
Is that sanitary?
那样卫生吗？
Maybe if we boil it.
煮开应该就可以了
8TH PARTY SCHARF, THIRD-CLASS MAGE
（第八小队 三级魔法使 夏鲁夫）
EHRE, SECOND-CLASS MAGE
（第八小队 二级魔法使 艾露）
What a pain.
还真是麻烦
I wanted to kill you with that shot.
我本想让你一击毙命
I'm surprised you reacted in time.
没想到你竟能及时反应过来
Well, whatever. Leave the cage with the Stille and go.
算了 留下关着陨铁鸟的笼子 然后滚蛋吧
What if we say "no"?
如果我们拒绝呢？
Then there's no use talking.
那就多说无益了
The lake is over there.
是湖那边的方向
She froze the lake!
她把湖冻住了！
What in the world is she thinking?
她究竟在想什么啊？
This is not funny!
开什么玩笑！
This mana belongs to someone in the second party.
这个魔力属于第二小队的成员
What are they thinking?
她们在想什么？
Do they plan to turn all the other parties against them?
这是打算与所有小队为敌吗？
Come on! Hurry up and melt it!
这是在做什么？还不赶快融掉！
Denken, what should we do?
邓肯 怎么办？
That's just a waste of time and energy.
那只是白费时间跟力气罢了
13TH PARTY DENKEN, SECOND-CLASS MAGE
（第十三小队 二级魔法使 邓肯）
There's no point in melting it.
融化冰面也没有意义
13TH PARTY RICHTER, SECOND-CLASS MAGE
（第十三小队 二级魔法使 利希塔）
With this much magic used on it,
湖水被注入这样大量的魔力后
no Stille will approach this lake anymore.
陨铁鸟再也不会接近这座湖了
We will steal the Stille from the second party.
就从第二小队手上偷走陨铁鸟吧
Seeing how much of a ruckus they made,
她们敢这样大动作冻湖
they must have worked out a plan to catch a Stille.
一定是准备好了捕捉陨铁鸟的计划
Mistress Frieren, what are you planning to do?
芙莉莲大人到底打算做什么呢？
Let's split up for now.
我们分头行事吧
Hurry up and melt the frozen lake!
赶快把湖面解冻！
How foolish.
真是愚蠢
If you use this much magic to melt the ice,
用这么多魔力融化冰面
this lake will really become useless.
这座湖就真的没用了
No Stille will come near here anymore.
不会再有陨铁鸟靠近这里了
Let's go.
我们走吧
Yeah. That way!
嗯 往那边走！
Those who have realized that fact
明白这一点的人
are searching for other bodies of water.
已经开始寻找其他水源了
But their mana detection is so poor.
但他们感知魔力的能力太差了
They won't be able to fend off dangers that lurk in the sky.
没有办法抵挡空中盘旋的威胁
How amateur.
真是菜鸟
The second party froze the lake!
第二小队冻住了湖面！
Are they trying to ruin the exam?
难道她们打算在考试乱来吗？
"Ruin"? That's not it.
“乱来”？才不是
This is the second party's elaborate plan.
这是第二小队周密的计划
We can't do anything until we figure out what that plan is.
在弄清楚她们的计划前 不能轻举妄动
The monsters got to them.
他们被魔物抓住了
They're dead.
已经死了
Let's go.
走吧
Old man, let's at least let them down.
爷爷 至少放他们下来吧
I'm sure you notice, don't you?
我相信你也注意到了吧？
They're circling up above.
在空中盘旋的魔物
It's not just one or two of them.
可不是只有一两只而已
They've put a spell on the dead bodies.
尸体被它们施加了魔法
If you try to let the bodies down, they can detect that.
一把尸体放下来 它们马上就会察觉
They're Geisels.
那是尸诱鸟
They use these hunting methods to lure in their next prey.
它们用这种方式狩猎下一个猎物
This party fell right into their trap
这支小队落入了它们的陷阱
and was annihilated.
因此被歼灭了
It's not normal
还真不寻常
to choose a place with monsters like these for an exam.
试场竟会选在有这种魔物出没的地方
It's as if they don't care if the candidates die.
简直就像毫不在意考生的死活一样
Oh right, it's your first time taking the first-class exam.
拉奥芬是第一次参加 一级魔法使选拔测验吧
The reason is quite simple.
这么做的理由很简单
People who die this easily
这么容易就死掉的家伙
are not fit to be first-class mages.
根本不配成为一级魔法使
The Continental Magic Association
大陆魔法协会
is concerned about the quality of first-class mages.
可是非常看重一级魔法使的质量呢
Some people are still fantasizing about
有些人至今还沉浸在
the strong, proud mages that were around when we were fighting the Demon King.
与魔王对战的时期 以为现在还有那样强大高贵的魔法使
Talk about being behind the times.
真的是跟不上时代了
I'm surprised, Denken.
我很意外 邓肯
I thought you were one of those who advocate that.
我本以为你也支持这种想法
Quality doesn't matter when it comes to mages.
魔法使的质量并不重要
First-class mages
一级魔法使
have to be a symbol of authority, nothing more than that.
只需要成为权势的象征即可
No matter how skilled you are as a mage,
不管身为多高强的魔法使
you are powerless if you cannot win over the hearts of people.
赢不了人心也一样没有影响力
I have seen my fair share of mages who are
我已见过很多比我还优秀的魔法使
far superior to me, fall from power and suffer persecution.
失去权势后 受到迫害的样子
People fear immense power.
人都会惧怕强大的力量
Authority based on fear is short-lived.
筑基于恐惧的政权维持不了多久
Plus, magic is nothing to be proud about anyway.
何况魔法也不是什么值得说嘴的事
I see.
原来如此
So being as weak as you is the perfect balance, huh?
所以像你这样弱简直刚刚好吧？
Aren't you getting cocky, youngster.
年轻人不要得意忘形了
I can win against you with my eyes closed.
我闭着眼都能打赢你
We can't detect the second party at all.
完全感知不到第二小队
They must be concealing their mana and hiding.
一定是抑制魔力躲起来了
This place too…
这里也是
It's the same as all the other bodies of water we've seen.
至今所有找到的水源都是一样的情形
It's not much, but the water is infused with mana.
虽然很少 但是水中已经被注入了魔力
I don't detect anything.
我什么都感知不到
-Can you? -I can't either.
-你能吗？ -我也不行
Did the second party do this?
这是第二小队做的？
Even the very person who infused it may not be able to detect it.
恐怕就连 注入魔力者本人都很难察觉到
That is how subtle it is.
就是这么微弱的量
But a Stille will be able to detect it.
但陨铁鸟就能感知到
They won't come near this water anymore.
它们不会再接近这片水源了
What's the point in doing this?
这么做有什么用吗？
I see! There must be a body of water that's not infused with mana.
原来是这样！ 一定有一处水源还未注入魔力
And the second party will most definitely be near that.
第二小队一定就在那附近
How do we find it?
那要怎么找到那里呢？
-I'm going to take a break. -Denken…
-我要稍微休息一下 -邓肯…
The exam location is huge.
考试场地很大
There's no way to find mages who are hiding to the best of their ability.
想找到全力隐藏气息的魔法使 是不可能的
We'll wait.
就等吧
They will let us know their location anyway.
反正她们一定会 让我们知道她们的位置
I've infused mana into all the ponds and springs that I could find.
我已经在所有 找得到的水池跟泉水注入了魔力
Although, there may be water bodies that we don't know about.
但还是可能有我们不知道的水源
Just being able to limit the water that Stilles can use is enough.
能限制陨铁鸟用的水源就够了
Well then, I'll wait here for a Stille to come.
那我就在这里埋伏等待了
Seriously? Who knew you could make mana disappear completely.
真的假的？ 魔力是可以抑制到完全消失的吗？
It's not "completely."
没有到“完全”
If I move, a little bit of mana leaks out.
我动一下就会有魔力漏出来
-See? -I can't even tell.
-看吧？ -看不出来啊
We'll be on the lookout then.
那我们就去把风了
-Don't get in the way. -Shut up.
-你可别妨碍我 -吵死了
If only it was raining, I could be more useful.
要是下雨的话 我也能成为有用的战力的
Too bad the barrier is repelling everything.
可惜结界把所有东西都反弹出去了
Frieren, did you do it?
芙莉莲 到手了吗？
It was worth turning the other parties against us.
不枉我们不惜与其他小队为敌了
Now we can pass the first stage.
这样我们就通过第一阶段了
No…
不…
Found them.
找到了
As I thought, they used magic.
如我所料 她们用了魔法
No matter how skilled of a mage you are,
不管是多优秀的魔法使
there is no way to cover up this moment.
都无法在这种时刻隐藏自己
Someone detected us. We should hurry and--
有人感知到我们了 得赶快走…
I guess it's too late to run away.
看来要逃已经太晚了
Jubelade.
花瓣钢铁化魔法
Doragate.
石块飞弹化魔法
They're like cannonballs.
像石弹一样
She stepped back again.
她又退开了
Her moves are polished and flawless,
动作干净利落 没有半点破绽
but it's an outdated fighting style. It's like fighting with my grandpa.
这种战斗模式也太过时了 好像在跟我爷爷战斗似的
Ordinary offensive magic and defensive magic…
一般攻击魔法和防御魔法…
You're only using basic magic, huh?
你只用基础魔法吗？
Are you trying to hide your trump card?
是打算藏起自己的绝招吗？
I was told not to use anything other than basic magic in combat.
师父要我在战斗中只能使用基础魔法
So that's your master's policy, huh?
那就是你师父的教育方针？
Yes.
对
Apparently, that is more than enough to fight mages of this era.
用这种魔法对付这个时代的魔法使 就绰绰有余了
Is that right?
是这样吗？
There she goes again.
又来了
What is this strange sensation?
这种违和感是什么？
It feels as if I'm up against a seasoned mage or something.
好像在跟身经百战的魔法使对战似的
I sympathize with you. With that kind of fighting style,
我真是同情你 用那种作战方式
you would've been dead already if you were against Wirbel.
跟维亚贝鲁对打的话 你早就被干掉了
That wouldn't make sense.
那样的话很奇怪呢
Because you are the strongest one out of all of them, aren't you?
因为你们队上最强的是你 不是吗？
Wirbel has been fighting the remnants of the Demon King's army
维亚贝鲁是北部魔法队队长
as captain of the Northern Magic Corps.
多年来一直与魔王军残党战斗
His experience in combat is on another level.
他的实战经验完全是另一个水平
His magic has absolutely no class, is cowardly,
他的魔法毫无品行可言
and is only meant to bring him victory.
纯粹只为取胜
That girl who is fighting Wirbel
现在跟维亚贝鲁战斗的那个女孩
is probably going to get killed.
很可能会被杀掉
Is that so.
这样啊
-What kind of horror did you experience? -Next time,I will cut off the head.
-究竟见过了什么样的地狱啊？ -下次我会砍掉头
-I will take this one down. -They're strong.
-这家伙就由老夫打倒 -这家伙好强
-Interesting. Why don't you try? -What is this sound?
-有意思 放马过来啊 -这是什么声音？
You old fart.
老糊涂
"Necessary Killing."
《必要的杀戮 》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵